<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The King of Bohemia's vvelcome to Count Mansfield, and into the Palatinate vvith the defeat of Bauaria's and Monsieur Tilley's army, since his arriuall: (the King being there in person) their resolution to march into Bauaria. The papists feare of his good successe, and further progression: and many other remarkeable thinges concerning Brunswick and his actions. Faithfully taken out of the letters of best credit.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14985</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853931</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177418</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240925347</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18507.42</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S118724</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99853931e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The King of Bohemia's vvelcome to Count Mansfield, and into the Palatinate vvith the defeat of Bauaria's and Monsieur Tilley's army, since his arriuall: (the King being there in person) their resolution to march into Bauaria. The papists feare of his good successe, and further progression: and many other remarkeable thinges concerning Brunswick and his actions. Faithfully taken out of the letters of best credit.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed MDCXXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf, which is lacking, is probably blank--Folger Library catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11355.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11355 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177418:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177418:1"/>
            <p>THE KING OF BOHEMIA'S VVELCOME TO Count MANSFIELD, AND INTO THE PALATINATE: WITH THE DEFEAT OF <hi>Bauaria's</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Tilley's</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, since his Arriuall: (the King being there in person) Their resolution to March into BAVARIA: The <hi>Papists</hi> feare of his good successe, and further progression: And many other remarkeable thinges concerning BRVNSWICK and his Actions. <hi>Faithfully taken out of the Letters of best Credit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed MDCXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:177418:2"/>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si caelicolis furor arma dedisset,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aut si terrigenae tentarent astra gigantes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non tamen auderet pietas humana, vel armis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Velvotis prodesse Ioui: sortis{que} Deorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignarum mortale genus.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>Lucan. lib. 3. Bell. Ciuilis.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177418:2"/>
            <head>THE KING OF BOHEMIA'S Welcome into the PALATINATE with the last defeat of Monsieur TILLIES Army, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeble thinges there, and elsewhere.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE turmoyles of Europe hauing gotten an vpperhand ouer the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Peace of the Nations, haue likewise preuayled with the very dispositions and affections of the people, so that though neuer so good Letters of credit come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, they shall receiue a soyle of calumniation, euen by such, as yet know no cause, why they should traduce the writers: but speake at randome, as either some strange credulity trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports them, or their own passions ouersway reason and probability, and this is and hath beene reciprocall both betweene Papist and Protestants, since that fatall day in which the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was driuen out of <hi>Prague,</hi> and the magnanimous Queene taught a lesson to try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer misfortune; the Papist wondring at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and hauing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name for the intrusion, but Treason, turbulency and ambitious Vsurpation: The Protestant justifying the action, as the determination of an Electiue Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and that God had a worke in hand to propagate his Church and Religion. The Papist magnifying the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> as if it were impossible to withstand the Emperour, the Pope and King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant alledging, that both Pope and Emperour must
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177418:3"/>submit to the Controler of all Popes and Emperours, and if he haue a cause in hand there is no pleading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, nor can any arme of Flesh turne the frame of Heauen about.</p>
            <p>The Papist maintaining, that all Kings and Princes doe act one anothers part, and therefore in the secrets of Combination seeme not allow of Subjects to take vp Armes against their Princes, or that inferiours shall contest with superiours in matters of any opposition, wherein the Dignity of Soueraignty shall suffer dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution, or the presumption of homagers admit of aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation: The Protestant alledging, that it absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holdes in successiue Monarchies, where the Subiect is bound patiently to tollerate the persecution, rather then resist the power of the Prince by way of Hostility: But in Prouinces that are not tyed to so strict Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there may be Appologies made, and many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances produced to alledge the graunts of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and confirmations of Priuiledges, with the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of free Citties, euen against Emperors themselues, as in the Confession of <hi>Ausburgh:</hi> the manumitting of Townes, and the immunities of principallities, which either a Parliament hath consented vnto, a Prince rate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, money redeemed, or time effected and brought to passe: And in this manner is all the newes of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope tossed betweene vs, yea banded vp and downe as Balles against the boards of a Tenniscourt, till the stuffing flye out of the leather, and the game is ended, except there be a fresh supply.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding this diuision amongst vs, there is but one Truth in the Variation of all manner of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, yea in this last busines of <hi>Tillies</hi> defeat, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177418:3"/>hath comforted all honest hearts, there may be many circumstances, but the maine point is, the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> hath preuayled, and for his welcome into the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate</hi> found a better friend of Fortune (as wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely abuse that Character) then he expected, but because I will not be too sodaine with you in this ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tidings, giue me leaue not by way of digression, but by honest recollection of some former passages, to prepare and season your humours the better to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that you desire, or if you be of a contrary humor, to admit of that you cannot preuent or disappoint.</p>
            <p>I will meddle with nothing, that shall reuiue your memories with matters distastfull: For that, which the Papist calls the worst, is subiect to construction and disputation, and for the rest neuer was the time or the Aduersary, so powerfull and ouer daring, but there was interceptions and casting of blockes in his fairest walkes and strongest courses of security. In the losse of <hi>Prague,</hi> the King was not altogether destituted and abandoned, but found a retiring place and friendly succors in <hi>Holland.</hi> In the reuolts of <hi>Silesia</hi> and <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi> the Marques of <hi>Ieggendorse</hi> made some stop of that inundation, and hath still and still beene faithfull and loyall to the generall Cause. In the bringing in of a strange Nation into <hi>Hungary,</hi> I meane the Spaniard in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Rab, Camora, Presburgh,</hi> and the rest; the Lords and Proceres brought in the Prince of <hi>Transiluania,</hi> which for any thing I see will not be so easily remoued or thrust out againe: In the mustring the Forces of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria,</hi> and proceedings of the Emperour, I hope the Deaths of <hi>Dampiers</hi> and <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> pull'd him back by the sleeue from running too fast to ouer presumption of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177418:4"/>preuayling: In bringing in <hi>Spinola</hi> into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> our few English, and the Forces of the Princes, reba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the fury of their Tryumphs, and made a kinde of Circle, that those Spirits could come no further, then limitation: In the donation of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> to <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> as a recompence of his seruice for taking of <hi>Prague,</hi> I finde no great cause of exaltation, for both he and <hi>Tilley</hi> are withstood, and peraduenture the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> himselfe repines at the matter, and may stand Newter for any thing the Emperour knowes, and then God knowes how the wheele of Fortune may be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about, and a new face of alteration quickely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske it selfe, to the comfort of all honest hearted loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers on, and the dismay of such, as either wished the thriuing of the Emperour, or pittyed the Palatine as a forlorne and forsaken man.</p>
            <p>But now if I should demaund from whence comes Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who raised vp the Duke of <hi>Bruns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick?</hi> who caused the Princes to remember themselues and their Honours? who put into the Emperors heart to send into <hi>England</hi> about a Peace? And in a worde who hath thrust so many Countries, and so much trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure into a Strangers hands, as you see by the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the Bishopricke of <hi>Spires</hi> and elsewhere, either you must answer with the Protestant, it is the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God to make <hi>Ahabs</hi> little Cloud powre downe shewers of Raine, to the refreshing the parched Land: or hang downe the head like a Bul-rush with the Papist, and cry out, that a bad cause doth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thriue against expectation, and men are tryed in this world to prepare them to patience, and other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durances.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177418:4"/>
            <p>Notwithstanding all this, and that I haue shew'd you, the <hi>Bohemia</hi> cause was neuer so desperate, but there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared heat and light in the Imbers, to manifest there might yet a fire be made out of the smaller sparkes; there are certaine men will neuer beleeue any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their owne humors, or if they be brought to a kinde of yeelding to the truth, they will interpose di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, Fortune, circumstances, desertion of friends, disorder of Souldiers, and such like, and therefore I will honestly proceed in the businesse of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> to this very houre, whereby you may see, that God made a hard, intemperate, and frostie Winter bring forth springing Flowers of comfort and prosperitie.</p>
            <p>I will not intermeddle with the disposition of other Princes, or the resolutions of Gouernment, either in affecting, or dis-affecting the cause: but come neerer vnto you and say, that while the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> lay at the <hi>Hage,</hi> many Treatises, Messages, and Counsells passed betweene the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> Himselfe, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the two Dukes of <hi>Brunswicke,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Vnion,</hi> Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Transiluania, Ieggendorff,</hi> Generall <hi>Vere,</hi> and many more, who all resolued (by one meanes or other) to reintegrate the distressed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or make him some recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for the losses of his Countrey.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> being the onely stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Spirit in these glorious Designes, vnderstanding that the <hi>Emperor</hi> was capitulating with the <hi>Hungarians</hi> for a Truce, and had sent <hi>Bauaria's</hi> Duke to take pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and surprise <hi>Heidelberg</hi> it selfe, after the Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> was departed from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177418:5"/>betweene whom some emulation arose, of which I will not dispute, concluded with the Marquis of <hi>Ieggendorff</hi> to diuide the Souldiers, being then in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauia,</hi> and follow <hi>Bauaria,</hi> which way soeuer he went: This he did with that brauery and expedition, that he startled him from <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> draue them into the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Spiers</hi> Country, remoued the siege of <hi>Francken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> visited <hi>Mainheim,</hi> where Sir <hi>Horace Vere,</hi> and most of the English lay, and supplied the wants of many places, which before were ouer-pressed with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of feare &amp; terror, of vtter defeat and expugnation.</p>
            <p>Then he made a martiall progresse through many Countries, and as <hi>Caesar</hi> was wont to write, <hi>Veni, Vidi, vici,</hi> he might well say, he came no where but they made some composition with him. For, like a Ball of Snow in frosty weather, by the often rowling, groweth bigger and bigger; so did his Armie increase, and the Countries where he came, supplied their wants. Thus did he visite <hi>Spiers, Wormes,</hi> and all those Bishoprickes: Thus came he into <hi>Leopaldus</hi> Countrey, and tooke many Townes, with <hi>Elsas Saueren</hi> it selfe. Thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded he to <hi>Mentz, Strasburgh,</hi> and many Catholicke Citties, who redeemed their peace with great store of treasure. Thus did he visite <hi>Loraine,</hi> and made a truce with the Duke for three yeares: And thus when he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood of Monsieur <hi>Tillies</hi> crueltie, and threatning of <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> he returned toward the <hi>Palatinate</hi> againe, both to lay downe a cooling Card for his ostentation, and breath new comfort into the decayed estate of those places.</p>
            <p>By this time, Aprill begins both with them and with vs, and Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> sends foure Regiments of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177418:5"/>Souldiers into <hi>Mainheim,</hi> and the Townes adioyning, tarrying with the rest of his Army at <hi>Germersheim,</hi> and <hi>Determi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> spoyling <hi>Bergausen, Dilsperg, Mandech, Mutterstat, Reinganhem, Manenheim,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where he quartred his Forces: then he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to fortifie many Townes and Sconses, and put Garrisons into them; for by this time he had taken in almost all the Bishopricke of <hi>Spiers,</hi> the strong Castle of <hi>Magdenburg,</hi> the townes of <hi>Haggenaw, Landenburg, Steine,</hi> and <hi>Elsas,</hi> all which he left sufficiently guarded, both to defend themselues against any enemy, and to command the Countrey to supply them with money and prouision. But because his particular actions haue inuited you to the superuising of many Pamphlets, I will speake no more of the same, but conclude, that by this time he heard of the King of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> comming to him, and so tarried for him at <hi>Haggenaw,</hi> and about <hi>Mainhem,</hi> and when he came in deed (as you shall heare hereafter) well-commed him with 18000. foote, and 6000. horse, the rest of his army possessing the Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke of <hi>Spiers,</hi> and commanding other places in <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paldus</hi> his Country; and thus much for <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> repayred into his distressed <hi>Palatinate.</hi> Now to <hi>Brunswick,</hi> and how he began and proceeded.</p>
            <p>While the King and Queene of <hi>Bohemia</hi> lay at the <hi>Hage,</hi> and had certaine newes, that his mother was retired to <hi>Wittenberg</hi> both for her better safetie, and better accommodating: <hi>Christian</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunswick,</hi> and younger brother of that house came to present his service to the Queene, his neere kinsewoman, and was honorably welcommed of the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177418:6"/>animated by the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> himselfe, who see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him forwarde, young, lustie, and valiant thought him a fit instrument to play his masters prise in these turbulent times, &amp; crosse affaires, whereupon amongst them they supplied him with a small Armie and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, wherein and whereby hee had such fortunate successe, that the Bishop of <hi>Collen,</hi> a Prince Elector, was afraid of him, and at last compelled to send to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> and the Spanish Garrisons for succours, which was accordingly granted him: For <hi>Bavaria</hi> and his Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> playing the wantons with the poore Townes, and the trod-vpon vines of the Pallatinate, and taking advantage of Count <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, euen as farre as the borders of <hi>Loraine,</hi> sent both horse and foote, yea <hi>Tilly</hi> once or twise went out in person to encounter with <hi>Brunswick,</hi> besides the Bishop obtained succours and commanders from <hi>Wesell</hi> and <hi>Gulick,</hi> and all to meete with this youthfull servant of <hi>Mars,</hi> who in my conscience emulating Count <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feilds</hi> glory, and desiring to imitate him in all vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, advanced himselfe the sooner, and the forewarder on the Martiall Theater, and as you haue likewise heard, prevailed in many skirmishes, and had the glory of as many victories. For he vexed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, came to <hi>Pater-borne</hi> and <hi>Westphalia,</hi> compounded with the Villages, expulsed the Bishop to some Castle of securitie, and had faire language euen of the Citty it selfe: thus increased hee to 1200 strong, possessed divers peeces of Ordnance, and fire workes, had sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie supplies from <hi>Bream,</hi> and other Princes, was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured that the <hi>Lantsgraue</hi> of <hi>Hesse,</hi> &amp; the Princes of the <hi>Vnion</hi> would come to a new composition with Fortune
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177418:6"/>for the recovery of their credits, and so resolved to goe forward for the King of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> designements, and did indeede doe many things worthy the honour of a better experienced Commander.</p>
            <p>When the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> saw the breaking out of this light from the thickning clouds of the former discomfiture; and apparent signes manifested vnto him of better hopes, but especially when hee vnderstood that the Emperour had sent Count <hi>Swatzenhourg</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England about a treatie of peace, hee began to bestirre himselfe and indeede was afraid he might bee countermaunded in his great prosecutions; For his suspition arose from these grounds.</p>
            <p>First from the Princely disposition of the King his Father in law to peace, who studied nothing more then to avoid the effusion of blood, and keepe one even course of charitie, noblenesse, and correspondencie with all Princes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from a determination in England to send the Lord of <hi>Belfast,</hi> who had beene <hi>Irelands</hi> Deputy, and a long well deserving Souldier, into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> about the rendition, or composition for the same, which though hee thought was no fit recompence for his losses and spoyles there, yet was it a gladnesse and a matter of consequence, because the sooner it was cleered of Enemies, the sooner it might recouer her pristinate florishing and handsomnes, onely he feared least so great a benefite imparted by the King of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland with the insupportable charges he had beene at before, and must be tied to now, would be a kinde of barre and procrastination of his other purposes, and finall resolutions.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:177418:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly, From the nature and manner of the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> Embassie, with the attraction of the person to win his purpose, (for what euer the Papists say, the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> desired no peace, but still thought vpon and proiected the recouery of his honor.) Now <hi>Swatzen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> was a comely, Courtly Gentleman, of a good presence, and habituall vertues, to effectuate any busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, hauing made a kind of composition to goe into <hi>England</hi> at his owne charge, and performe this seruice by way of gratuitie, and recompence to his imperiall Maiestie, for his procuring him a wife, which belike both pleased his affection, and aduanced his estate.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, From a new assurance of the discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Prague,</hi> who desired once againe to see him at the head of some sufficient troupes, and to make him recompence for their former desertion.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, from the strength of his own friends, who were now able to muster an Army, greater then any in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom,</hi> &amp; therfore why shuld a peace countermand his forwardnes, &amp; pul him back in the race to a new glory.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, From the Emperors weake preparations; for there were few Forces raised, and lesse money in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines: Besides, the Army out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and the treasure from <hi>Spaine</hi> failed in the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> and amongst the <hi>Swiss,</hi> whereby <hi>Leopaldus</hi> was much discontented, and discountenanced; yea, out of hope to recouer his losses in his Country, and so had cause to complaine, but no meanes of redresse.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, From the repinings of the Duke of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> who had disputed the matter with a messenger from the <hi>Emperor,</hi> about the donation of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> from the heires of the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to a stranger, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177418:7"/>must needs breed an innouation among the Prouinces: For neither was the <hi>Emperor</hi> to challenge the Empire as hereditary to <hi>Austria,</hi> nor to inflict the children of any Prince with such a punishment, for the Fathers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, be it treason, or what you will.</p>
            <p>Eightly, Last of all, from the intermixture of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, which now made him more zealous to expell <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and superstition out of his <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and take pitty on the teares of so many thousand Protestants, who euery where began to complaine of the crueltie of the Bishops, and the tyranny of the Iesuits that thun dred out nothing but warre, and reuenge, blood and death, fire and spoile, hell &amp; damnation against them.</p>
            <p>All which things considered, hee thought it high time to come to prevention, and approch neerer and neerer to some publick practise of anticipation, least the mischeife should grow incurable, and the vexation remediles: This as you haue heard made him hassard his person, and expose his Fortunes to a wonderfull and dangerous iourney: For in the first weeke of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill (some will haue it on a Sunday,) hee resolved to retire privately from the <hi>Hage,</hi> and sent Sir <hi>Francis Nethersall</hi> to <hi>Dort,</hi> to provide him a ship, but not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the busines: so with onely 10, persons disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and a small Cabinet of Iewels, hee embarked himselfe, and landed at <hi>Callice,</hi> from whence he tooke wagon for <hi>Amiens,</hi> where some will haue him discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, insomuch that the Governour taken with his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heroick demeanour, offered him his service, and resolved to entertaine him according to his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and worth, but it should seeme, hee refused all ceremonie: for he onely requested taciturnity, and so
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177418:8"/>went forward on his iourney: but whether it hapned in this particular, or no, it matters not, sure I am, hee went safe from <hi>Amiens,</hi> and as some will haue it, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red two wagons through the wood, and a <hi>Provost Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall</hi> to accompany him, hauing good Petronels and other weapons amongst them, in which manner they came to <hi>Sedan,</hi> not yet discovered: but when the Duke of <hi>Bolloigne,</hi> who being very old kept his Pallace here vnderstood of his accesse, and by former letters was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised of his intent, and purpose, hee rose to meete him and in such a fashion, that it was quickly noysed ouer the Couutrey, shhat an escape he had made: but notwithstanding his great entertainement heere, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined not to tarry, nor did the Duke thinke it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, that rumor should any way prepare his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for his interception, so within a day or two hee provided a sufficient convoy for him: and he came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Easter first to <hi>Landaw,</hi> secondly to <hi>Germshen,</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to <hi>Haggenaw,</hi> and last of all to <hi>Mainhem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you must consider, that a little before his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, Count <hi>Mansfeild:</hi> the <hi>Margraue</hi> of <hi>Turso,</hi> Generall <hi>Vere,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Overtrout,</hi> had beene in counsell at <hi>Mainhem</hi> aboue two houres, which dissolued, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their quarters, and Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> prepared an Armie to goe meete the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which was not, nor could be so couertly done, but the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Tilley</hi> had notice of the same, who newly returned from being fleshed with the blood of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, as sparing neither man, woman, nor child, in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain villages betweene <hi>Heidelberg</hi> &amp; <hi>Mainhem,</hi> in which iollitie they attempted to set vpon the Reare of Count <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> Army, alreadie on foote for some enterprise,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177418:8"/>and defeated some of his Foot &amp; some of his Waggons. For when he vnderstood that <hi>Mansfield</hi> had made a long march and was remote from the place, and knew the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons of <hi>Franckendale</hi> and <hi>Mainhem,</hi> safe from issuing out, or making any Sallies, he tooke the aduantage, and set vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the stragling Company, and so in a iollity returned to his Quarter.</p>
            <p>By this time is the King welcommed to the Army, or as some haue it, returned with the same, which went to meet him: and so came to <hi>Mainhem,</hi> where a whole day was spent in Ceremony, and obseruation toward him, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that some will haue reciprocall teares, &amp; passionate imbraces betweene him and Sir <hi>Horace Vere;</hi> yea not an <hi>English</hi> man passed without shaking by the hand, &amp; Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankfulnes: the extacy betweene <hi>Mansfield</hi> &amp; him had her determination the day before, and to adde to the ioy of this welcome, the people brought in their presents, and euen from <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and <hi>Bazill,</hi> the Riuers were filled with Boates, who came downe on heapes to see their Prince, and shew their Duty, so that whereas before Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Butter, and good accates seldome fell to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals share: the common Soldier now renued his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance euen with Pullen, Fowle, Fish, and Pastery, yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a dainty dish.</p>
            <p>Well, time addes a period to all thinges, and their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires put them in minde of other busines: For you must consider, that both <hi>Gonzales Cordua</hi> and the Spaniards, and <hi>Bauaria</hi> and <hi>Tilley</hi> with their Colonels, and Captaines, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand of all this, and demeaned themselues like vndan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Souldiers for all the alteration: <hi>Gonzales</hi> and his Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards lying in <hi>Openheim, Crusnach,</hi> and other places, kept their former reposednes, and neuer shewed a motiue of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177418:9"/>distemperature, or any passion for the newes: But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture stood vpon a Guard of better circumspection, and strengthned their Watches with ouerlooking the Fortifications: <hi>Tilley</hi> was brauer then euer, mustring his Forces, drawing out his Army, and increasing it with <hi>Bauaria's</hi> new supply: For you must consider, that not two dayes before the King of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> arriuall, the Emperour had sent a Meslenger to Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the cessation of Armes, and certaine other Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions concerning the good of Christendome, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification of the present troubles, who quickly returned answer, that hee was now but a second person, and must yeeld to a higher Soueraignty, for the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was come in person into the Field; neither was this Answer pleasing to the Emperour nor the Title, yet for the time making a Vertue of patience, he depended on a better satisfaction: and sent such Forces as he could into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> with whom <hi>Tilley</hi> proiected great matters.</p>
            <p>All this while Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> lyes in wayte for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, and so leauing the King to ouerlooke the Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of <hi>Mainhem,</hi> &amp; <hi>Franckendale:</hi> where he was made acquainted with the seuerall accidents and losses, which happened in the siege of <hi>Franckendale:</hi> He takes an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of <hi>Tilley's</hi> brauery, and acquaints the King with his purpose, who thereupon brauely resolueth to goe in person into the Field. But concerning that, time shall discouer more? It is now sufficient, and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently well, that vnderstanding, that <hi>Tilley</hi> was lodged within a Village not farre from the Towne, wherein he had left the memories of his Cruelty, and within foure Leagues of <hi>Heidelburgh,</hi> he layde an Ambuscado of 2000. Horse and Foote to entrap him. For as I said, he recided
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177418:9"/>a little remote from the mayne body of his Army, hauing onely two Regiments with him, being 3000. and at this time was somewhat carelesse, and lesse thought of a Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish, because he imagined the Enemy would bee detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from fighting, as busied in Welcomming the Prince, whereupon Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> likewise apprehending as much, and desiring of all other thinges to drawe him in person into the Field, came toward him with 600. Shot, and Pikes, and some few Horse, who seemed rather to braue him, then intended to Fight with him, and because hee should be the better induced to come neare the Ambuscado: Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> retired to the head of these obscure Troopes, and sheltred himselfe vndisco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered: the rest that were to Skirmish indeed, made onely shew, as if they had beene but Forragers, &amp; came of purpose to get prouision for the Army, but now being so neare the Enemy the Pikes made a stand, and the Shot began a Skirmish, the Horse wheeling about to drawe them to better ground, then the Valley they were lodged in, and played their partes so well, that <hi>Tilley</hi> would not be so affronted, but resolued to the Encounter, if they had beene as many more.</p>
            <p>Thus he drew forth himselfe, and his Captaines drew forth the rest, so that with 800. horse and somewhat more then 3000. foot, he gaue the Alarum to the Villages, that a fight was begun: but ere his maine Army could prepare it selfe, or Bauaria haue notice of the accident, the fight was begun, and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> with 2000. horse, and 500. Muskatieres presently enclosed them, and as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently disranked them all: For what with the suddainnesse of the businesse, and the feare of a greater Army, or the apprehension, that the King might be there in person, or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177418:10"/>the apparant fury of Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> charge, who was questionlesse exasperated against them: or the willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Souldier to be reuenged, who both remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred their owne wrongs, and his cruelty against the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants: there presently followed a lamentable slaughter: for the horse were rowted, and thronged so fast one vpon another, that they lay slaine by heapes: the foote (as all Souldiers know) once displaced, fell vnder the rage of the horse, yea were subiect to the foot, that kept their rankes, and came vpon them with violence: the shot had also a share in the execution, as they had afterwards in the spoile, <hi>Tilly</hi> himselfe fled, as peraduenture being better horsed, better breathed, and more cautelous, as apprehending the danger, and being more afraid to come within the danger of Captiuity: but whether he were hurt or no, is vncertaine.</p>
            <p>But now you must know, that the greatest cause of this discomfiture, came through <hi>Tillies</hi> owne hastinesse, who was so hot vpon these few Muskatieres, that he brake with his horse through his owne Pikes, who stood in their open order to giue him passage, and could not come in to forme and fashion againe, till certain Captaines of <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields</hi> horse espied the aduantage, and set vpon them at the first, as soone as the ambush brake out, and before they could rally themselues together.</p>
            <p>After the slaughter, which was reckoned very neere 2500. followed the spoile, many colours were taken, great store of Armes were shared, diuers prisoners reserued, all the cariages diuided, and many horse lest their Riders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them on the ground.</p>
            <p>To this you may adde, that while the Souldiers in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison drew themselues out to second their fellowes, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177418:10"/>Pesants of the places tooke aduantage of the few number, which remained, and cut their throats, whereby they sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose as much harme was done this way, as the other, and both wayes as is thought irrecouerable. I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of the Boonfires at Heidleberg, and prayers euery where. For this cause is generally so well reputed of that without disputation of the iustification of the warre, a world of friends come flocking in to the King, and in England the matter is so well affected, that both good and bad wish well vnto the Queene: yea, the young Princes, who were neuer seene amongst vs, are pittied of all sorts, to be depriued of their Fathers inheritance, and disinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the malignity of time, and the ouer-sight (as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist will haue it) of their Father. But of that no more. It is sufficient now to see the people glad, and heare their tongues eccho out their hearts wishes, and all for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity of the Palatinate, wherein I shall not be beleeued, if I tell you the friends which are raised, the helps promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, the prayers made, the contribution prepared, and the meanes discouered for the restauration. For the Duke of Wittenberg is ready, and hath diuers forces mustered, which the Emperour repines at, and goeth about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept: but because the Kings Mother is in his Court, and that there may be better vse of them in his Countrey, to defend the same, and be in a readinesse at more neede. It hath beene agreed vpon by a Counsell of Warre, that he shall detaine them there, and stand the better vpon the Guard of opposition, if the Emperour enforce him, or as he hath done, command him to attend Bauaria, or whom he shall appoint.</p>
            <p>The Marqnesse of Baden hath also sent word, that his Army is 10000. and longs to ioyne with Count <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177418:11"/>but especially to see the King of Bohemia, whose case according to the fortune of great persons in aduersity, is now much lamented, considering it might haue beene a temptation to haue ouercome any of them all, who euer reputed Bohemia subiect to election, and the choise of the Lords, and as for the King, hee came not in with an Army, nor proiected to fortifie his owne Countrey: but tooke an honorable retinue with him, and would not out of suspition giue the Emperour cause of iealousie, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his owne ambition hastned him to the dignity, or any pollicy or bribery had wrought the Lords and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors vnder-hand to preferre him before another.</p>
            <p>The Duke of Brunswick is great with the birth of some braue action in his behalfe, and longs for the deliuery, but is aduised to remaine, where hee doth, and send to the Lantzgraue of Hess for his forces, that he may both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the Bishop of Cullen: and attend <hi>Saxony,</hi> to know what he will doe either in Silesia or Bohemia: For now is the time of the busines, and of the yeere, so that if he hold his peace at this time, he may for euer hereafter be silent. To talke of the elder Brunswick, or the Marquesse of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg, were onely to fill vp a Catalogue with names without actions: For their Countries are so remote, that they may doe more good with their purses, then their persons, wherein I make no question they will be indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and considering so many motiues of assistance, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue my selfe the disbursing of treasure shall not be a wall of seperation betweene the Kings cause, and their care, and shal leaue them to the due examination of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which shall as much enlarge their own honour, as augment his dignity.</p>
            <p>These are the greater circles, which moue in this Sphere
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177418:11"/>of turbulency, concerning the businesse of Europe, and the difficulties of Warre, which as it is begun, so in plaine termes cannot end without effusion of blood, and raising vp of stormes; nay, I am afraide, that as the Sea exagita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted remaines stormy, and full of high billowes after the winde is laid, so will it fall to Europes share: let these contentions be pacified, when they can, the heires of these Princes, and the seedes of discention may remember for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vnkindnesse, and sprowt vp againe, as the ground is either nourished or manured, except (which is heere not to be spoken of) the causes of the Warre, and occasion of the grieuances might be either stifled in their infancie, or digged vp in their full growth, and firme flourishing, root and all.</p>
            <p>To conclude in a word, this defeat of Monsieur <hi>Tillie</hi> was the 12. or 14. of April. They purpose to haue 2. armies made of these forces, the 1. for <hi>Bauaria,</hi> the other for <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia.</hi> They will haue the King to admit of no peace, &amp; yet submit to the Maiestie of England. And they will haue an absolute expulsion of the Iesuites, wheresoeuer they come, and punishment of the Catholick Priests, that haue stored their inuectiues with vnciuill termes, and odious defamation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177418:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177418:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>